[Music]
well on behalf of Ralston college and
the Cambridge Center for the Study of
Platonism it's an immense honor to
introduce two of the foremost
intellectuals of our age these thinkers
Warner philosopher the other a
psychologist are spiritual writers
addressing the malaise of the soul in
our culture John Stuart Mill in his
magnificent essay on Coleridge wrote of
Bentham Jeremy Bentham who above all
others men have been led to ask
themselves in regards to any ancient or
received opinion is it true and by
Coleridge what is the meaning with
Coleridge in contrast to the utility of
Bentham the very fact that any doctrine
had been believed by thoughtful men and
received by whole nations and
generations of mankind was part of the
problem to be solved was one of the
phenomena to be accounted for this I
think is true of both Roger Scruton
and Jordan Peterson and I'd like to
mention just a couple of points of
convergence warned is an insistence on
the importance of imagination as
conversion to truth in opposition to a
mere fantasy and an opposition to
idolatry ideology as well as idolatry
especially the idolatrous ideology of
the postmodern Foucault derived
consensus and an urgent return to
questions about truth beauty and
goodness and of course part of this is
linked to what both perceive as the
perilous position of the modern
University they both argue that
continuity of esteem needs to be
Regained in the humanities and that the
dominant strands of the humanities are
leading to an impoverishment of the
souls of students narratives both argue
are not just stories of power but these
narratives persist because of their
truth so the importance for both Ralston
college and indeed for the Cambridge
Center for the Study of Platonism both
of these thinkers is their insistence
upon the relationship between muthos and
Lagos between story and reason the
insistence upon a hierarchy of values
and their vision of Education as
conversion to truth this conversation
will be moderated by the president of
Ralston College Stephen Blackwood Thank
You Douglas for those inspiring and
grounding words starting us off right in
relation to the past that we wish to
recover
let me start I think with a very
straightforward but perhaps difficult
question where we were gathered around
the theme apprehending the transcendent
loosely to gather this conversation and
I'd like to begin by asking each of you
what is the transcendent what does it
mean for something to be transcendent
well if you let me start I take a
position which I attribute also to Kant
that that we have a very clear negative
understanding of it we as it were
advanced to the edge of our thinking in
so many areas knowing that although
there's nothing further that we can say
that somehow the truth
nevertheless not run out and that
negative view I think needs to be
combined with a more positive view which
tells us that there are other ways not
just maybe not thinking but some other
way of crossing that boundary and as it
were landing in the realm of the
transcendent and knowing it from inside
I think you know and that this is
something that we understand very
quickly in personal relations you know
that when I when I address you I know
that I'm addressing something which
addresses me too but from a place where
I could never be I couldn't look at
myself from those eyes and I can't
capture the thing that is looking at me
from those eyes but nevertheless there
are leaps of the imagination which can
put me in your point of view
and from that point view I can come to
understand exactly what I am but in a
completely different way from simply the
ordinary empirical knowledge that I have
of myself and I think that that sort of
interpersonal understanding I would say
we can adapt to all the other aspects of
our world which are mysterious to us
music for instance that's a beginning
and I want to return to music a bit a
bit later Jordan I think it's useful as
an adjunct to that so so Sir Roger
mentioned that the transcendent is what
we bump up against when we realize our
ignorance and so it's that which
transcends our ignorance and and that in
itself makes it an implacable fact
unless you believe that you have no
ignorance in which case there's no point
in furthering a discussion with you so
the transcendent is the fact insofar as
it's that which transcends our ignorance
but you can also think about it
technically so and and and I think we
know enough about how the brain works
now so that not that we know much so
that useful things can be said about
that I you tend to represent
the world in the simplest manner that
you possibly can that works for what
you're doing and so you don't actually
see the world you see sufficiently
useful low represent low resolution
representations of the world and if they
work then that's fine there's no need to
adjust them and they're relatively easy
to remember and to manipulate but now
and then you have a misapprehension
about someone let's say and you have a
conversation with them and the
conversation goes sideways and what that
means is that the the thing that you
thought you were conversing with is not
the thing that you're conversing with
and that manifests itself in error right
so error is the place where the
transcendent reveals itself and what is
actually revealing itself is the reality
that's outside and underneath your
perceptions and so what you see in the
world in some sense is a set of animated
cartoons and a lot of that is actually a
consequence of you seeing nothing but
your memory because your brain is
organized so that instead of going
through all of the difficulty of having
to look at the thing in itself you look
at what you assume to be there and if
you can get away with that so much the
better
but the thing in itself is always much
richer richer than your apprehension of
it which is partly why you make mistakes
but also partly why you can continue to
garner wisdom in the world there's
always more there than meets the eye and
god only knows how much more there's
there than meets the eye and you can
show this even in the religious sense to
some degree because you could say that
there's an element to the transcendent
that instills people with a sense of
religious significance you can do that
by immediately scientifically by feeding
people chemicals for example that
disrupt the inhibition of perception by
memory and then that puts them in a
place where the transcendent tends to
reveal itself sometimes an overwhelming
force so this it's not some fiction that
this exists it's the what's transcendent
is more real than the reality that you
perceive well let's pick let's pick up
on that because the the the ancients in
the medieval had a clear sense that it
wasn't the world that was
it was we ourselves as we make an ascent
towards deeper truths higher forms of
the beautiful as we ourselves become
more self-conscious so it's not the
world that's changing but but us I
wonder if we could say how you
understand the nature of that ascent
that that that that that movement and
and what brings it about well I I would
be a bit wary of the metaphor of ascent
you know I I think in Plato it's quite
clear what he meant he wanted us to
actually to transcend our earthly
perceptions and our earthly way of
seeing things and look on the world from
from a God's eye perspective and this
could be done if we enter the world of
the pure forms and so on leave empirical
reality behind I think actually insofar
as the experience of the transcendent
that I as I understand it is available
to us modern people it's not that way
that we get it perhaps about Sir Jordan
might be right that there are these
drug-induced experiences where things
open up to us because old barriers are
suddenly swept away but in my own case
it is the concentration on the empirical
reality which at a certain point flips
from mere sensory understanding to a
vision in that of its communicating
something to me and I think this is what
the literature and art and music do at
their best they they read ascribe
reality so that it is actually a
communicating something to you it's not
just there as an inert object before you
and that sense of the transcendence is
like discovering yourself in a mirror
seeing in the world as a whole that
thing in you that you could never
identify in words you know the subject
which is looking at it and it's not a
mystic mystery but it's something that
you can't then explain the different
between a good writer and a bad writer
of course is that a good writer will
describe something in such a way that
the thing described has the soul of the
reader in it so so that might be the
distinction in part between the thing
and the meaningful thing right and
that's a miss that's a very mysterious
phenomenon in fact in some sense the the
essence of phenomenon because that means
to shine forth no as we're surrounded by
empirical facts they're everywhere
there's more of them than we can
possibly count but some of them do
emerge and manifest themselves as that
as that conjunction between the factual
and the meaningful and then that's
what's gripping and if you're fortunate
I mean to me that's also partly what
what leads us onward and maybe in
something approximating the ascent that
you described is that the set of facts
manifests itself as implicitly
meaningful and that means in some sense
that there is a call to you that isn't
from within you I mean I don't know how
else to put it exactly because your walk
into a bookstore in a book will will
will reveal itself to you you know or or
you have a conversation and part of the
conversation will trigger something in
you or you're reading a scientific paper
and much of its dull and then all of a
sudden there's something that sparks
outward that's like a port that's a
portal into the transcendent and that is
a place where the fact and the meaning
converge and that's a phenomena we don't
understand very well it has something to
do with its convergence with the
narrative that drives us whatever that
happens to be yeah I think that's a good
way of putting it actually it connects
with the general problem of what the
humanities are in the university I've
always assumed that in some way or
another if you're teaching literature or
musicology or or history of art or
anything you are opening young people to
those moments when the world ceases to
be a mere accumulation of facts and as
it were addresses you and that requires
literary criticism it requires opening
yourself to experience in a way that it
requires a serious education of a
Elkind and i think that if we thought of
the humanities as directed towards that
we can see why they might be one way to
fill the moral void that grows so easily
in people's lives so young had this idea
which I really love it's a very
sophisticated idea it's it's it's his
idea of how the self first of all so the
self for young this Christ was a symbol
of the self so the logos was a symbol of
the self so that's sort of what would
you say it's the divine essence of
humanity and the image of that is a
symbol of the self and for young the
self was the totality of the individual
across time and space so it's whatever
you are as as a transcendent object
that's a good way of thinking about it
and then can imagine that that
transcendent object also has to interact
with you and the world moment by moment
and his belief was that those times when
that space of meaning opened up so there
is that convergence between the fact and
and the gripping of the fact was the
manifestation of the self which is this
transcendent object in the specific
moment of time and space and therefore a
call forward to move towards revealing
that totality as much as it can be
revealed and so it would be partly and
that would be partly revealed by then
following a meaningful pathway and it
would be the case that if you're engaged
in the teaching of humanities and
literature that you are trying to engage
exactly that part of the person it's to
pull them into the story and to and have
that open up to them and then that's a
portal it's not it's not words on paper
it's it's a portal to their to their
further development towards this this
the manifestation of this higher and
more transcendent mode of being that's
like the Hindu idea of the transition
from the samsara to Brahman isn't it
that you suddenly you pass through a
barrier that can't actually be described
because you can only know it when you're
on the other side of it and but when
you're on the other side of it you're
looking back at the thing that you've
left and seeing it in as it were for the
first
and knowing what it means I guess that's
a little connects a little bit with what
Douglas was saying about about coda
Ridge that you know that that Coleridge
was an advocate of a form of education a
form of knowledge which shows the
meaning of things as opposed to the mere
facts accumulated by Bentham and people
like that both of you have done quite
deep dives into twentieth-century
totalitarian ideologies and both of you
have been very trenchant critics of the
ideology the various forms of nihilism
in in our own culture but I think all of
us tire of a a kind of negativity that
has come to be very prevalent in in our
culture not simply the nihilism but then
we can criticize the nihilism we ought
to criticize it both of you have been
have been brilliant critics of it
but I what I take to be at work in both
of your in in in the work that both of
you do is is not fundamentally criticism
but a turn towards something positive a
a recovery of a sense of the
transcendent I'd like to have a that
have a turn for a moment to what does
that recovery look like where do we
start
well if we're thinking intellectually
the world of scholarship and education
that we both belong to has turned as you
say in this negative direction always
preferring debunking explanations of
everything so reducing them to the
lowest motive that it's not truth but
power that we pursue in all that through
kody and nonsense and I think the only
response that is to come up with bunking
explanations of so to speak try to put
back into the subject matter one's own
inherent belief in it and to recognize
that you know that when we're not around
on this earth for very
and we do have an obligation to find the
things that we love and not the things
that that we reject and that those
things that we love the best way towards
them is to look at the things that other
people have loved that's what a culture
is it's the residue of all the things
that people have thought worthwhile to
preserve and teaching that will again
reconnect us to what matters well and
there's there's also ways of providing a
pathway forward by making the Fukien
arguments let's say about power more
high resolution and one of the things
that I do in my lectures in my public
lectures that I think is rather comical
is to take an and poke fun in some sense
about the idea of power as the
fundamental foundation for the
hierarchical structures of the West I
think well you can think of the West as
one large-scale low-resolution
totalitarian tyranny the tyranny of the
patriarchy or you can decompose that
which is in some sense is to transcend
the concept and I think well I asked my
audience is what they think about the
the tyranny of plumbers or the tyranny
of massage therapists well because it's
it's dead relevant it's like let's say
you need a plumber and you do need a
plumber everyone agrees that you need a
plumber and because there's hell to pay
otherwise and so and then the question
is well how is it that you go about
selecting a plumber and the answer isn't
that there are roving bands of
tyrannical plumbers that go door-to-door
telling housewives that if they don't
use their services the service of the
most tyrannical plumber that there'll be
mafia-like consequences what what
happens instead is that you look for the
plumber who is most able in your
estimation and in the in the in his
reputation as distributed through the
community for being able to fix pipes
and run a business and engage in an
honest transaction with you and that's
competence that's not power you see in
what I see as most corrosive about the
postmodern type suspect
those who've derived themselves from
Foucault let's say is that the idea that
every hierarchy or the hierarchy as such
is predicated on power is actually an
assault on the idea of competence itself
and that in turn is an assault on the
idea that there are real problems that
can actually be solved well then if you
dispense with all that and it's only
power there's no real problems to be
solved and there's no noble ways of
solving them even even as in even in as
concrete a manner as a good plumber
would solve them which is a not not a
trivial thing
and so then you deprive people of you
deprive people of that of that sense of
purpose in their life even even at the
high resolution levels you know when
I've insisted in my lectures that you
know if you're the sort of person who
runs a small diner that it's incumbent
on you to run the highest quality small
diner that you possibly can because what
you're doing there is not merely
providing people with basic nutrition
there's way more to the space than meets
the eye and your noble what would you
say acceptance of your limited
responsibility is also simultaneously a
way to transcend that and that can be a
place where the neighborhood meets that
can be a place where tired people
revivify themselves before they go off
to do their difficult work that can be a
place where you can mentor your
employees and help them develop their
life like it's a rich it's an
unbelievably rich microcosm and to take
on the the care and aunt ending of that
microcosm as a responsibility is also a
great pathway to meaning and a necessary
and meaning is something that's well not
epiphenomena and not dispensable but
absolutely central to to human thriving
in the psychological and practical sense
yeah but we do have to try and
understand why it is that there is such
a charm in the Foucauldian position why
is it that people want to believe that
all the best things what we think of the
best things in human relations are
simply disguised forms of manipulation
you know that that the whole feminist
view of the relations in men and women
for instance which is founded on this
deep myth that men are exercising
exercise power as agender
to use the fashionable world the word /
/ women and that all study of this is
just a way of revealing that power and
and the capillaries through which it
flows you know I think there's a will to
believe this and why is one of the big
questions that I think we have to try to
understand is it that when people lose
some kind of transcendental religious
faith that they are automatically fall
into this great pit of resentment as of
the Nietzschean kind to try and find the
the oppressor in every relationship or
is there are there truths that they are
exploring as well is there are there
forms of power or forms of human
relation that look like power from one
aspect but are perhaps also look like
tenderness and dependence from another
aspect and that they've just are
emphasizing one half of it or something
like that I think there are they're real
questions as to how it is that our
culture has got into this position yeah
well that's the question below the claim
of power and so I mean I've thought
about that to some degree and here's
three possibilities I mean one is the
accusation that all there is is power is
the justification for use of power of
course so that's that's handy if that's
what you want to use so then then
there's another problem and that goes
along with the the failure the willful
failure to distinguish competence from
tyranny and power let's say because we
might think of power as unearned
Authority something like that because we
need a definition of power and I think
that there's a resentment at work there
that's very very deep I think it's it's
deep in the biblical sense which is that
there is a proclivity for those who do
not manifest what they could manifest in
the world and thereby fail to watch the
success of those who do manifest what
they could manifest
the world and succeed and become
embittered by that tremendously
embittered and then to label that is
power and then to attempt to destroy it
because it's simpler to do that than to
do the radical internal retooling that
would be required to set things straight
internally I'm sure that's right that
that's one explanation of why people are
always tempted by the zero-sum vision of
relations his benefit is my cost sort of
thing right yeah I wanted to pick up on
that that the the the very widespread
view that things are zero-sum which is
of course the language of power what's
the antidote to that what is that how
does one overturn the the ideology of
power how does one transcend that with a
nonzero-sum truth or approach to life I
personally would say that the first
thing to recognize is that there are
positive some games you know that's what
the the real theory of the market tells
us that there are whole realms of human
transactions where both parties gain
from from their shared engagement and
though that doesn't won't drive away the
real source of this this difficulty has
subdued what Jordan was referring to you
know that people's people's resentment
at the success of others when they
cannot match it or cannot easily match
it will not know or will not mention
which is evil works yes exactly and
because of the labor of re re conceiving
your own position in such that you
actually have to do something about it
you know that it's there are some
there's something lazy about the
zero-sum vision yeah but it's not a you
know it's not a vision that successful
people have you know any level of
reality and you can actually combat that
to some degree by make it high
resolution again by by making examples
just like because very few people
actually believe once they observe that
all the
Nation ships they've had with other
people have been zero-sum now you might
get some very disadvantaged people and
and these people do exist who've been
taken advantage by virtually everyone
they've ever encountered in their whole
life like that does happen but most of
the time all you have to do is remind
people it's like well think of someone
that you loved even briefly think of a
friend that you've had it's like well
you you successfully negotiated with
that friend to do things together
because otherwise it's not a friendship
and it has to be successful negotiation
which means your friend has to be happy
with what you were doing and you have to
be happy and so and then wasn't it the
case that you were both happy or doing
that then either of you would have been
doing something else alone and and isn't
that evidence in your own action and
your life for the existence of
nonzero-sum games and they're dependent
on successful negotiation is we can both
have more than we would otherwise have
if we can come to a consensus about what
we'll both pursue and it's very few
people when you make it personal like
that and high resolution again it's very
few people who are willing to pursue
their ideology of zero-sum of a zero-sum
reality so far down that they'll
actually use that to characterize their
most intimate relationships now I would
say that someone who does that by
temperament is literally psychopathic
because the psychopathic view of the
world is absolutely that it's a zero-sum
game yes I think that's right but of
course we have a whole body of
literature about sexuality which is
trying to establish that that that
sexuality is the exercise of power of
one person over another you get it
already in Sartre was Being and
Nothingness where he almost is almost by
logic that that a serious sexual desire
for him ends up as sadomasochism because
you cannot extract from the other that
gift of his freedom which which is what
you're looking for because his freedom
is his and not to be obtained by you and
therefore you can only do this by sort
of tearing at his flesh getting him to
confess in the extremes of agony
but he can't do it you know this kind of
thing I know that's a very perverted
vision of what sexual relations are but
you get that image used by Simone de
Beauvoir and all kinds of feminists to
essentially to D legitimize the idea
that there is such a thing as as love
for the other sex well there's there's I
think it also masks a more fundamental
problem that's really a biological
problem like it's a misapprehension of a
genuine problem
but part of what sex does is temporarily
subordinate the individual to nature and
the species and so there is a domination
there no and if if if a woman decides to
have a child then she is going to
undergo a series of extraordinarily
radical transformations and she's also
going to end up in a situation where in
all likelihood something else becomes
fundamentally more important than her
and there so there is a there's a sub it
might be voluntary subjugation but
there's a subjugation to nature and and
that's built into the fabric of
existence and I think it's very easy not
to want to grapple with that because
it's such a profound problem and then to
to make that as secondary consequence of
something like unbalanced power
relationships between the genders but of
course our traditional religion offers
you selves for this that the rite of
passage in which which joins man to
woman the rite of passage which makes
birth an experience of the whole
community and death likewise and you
know the sense also that in these great
events one is occupying a position in
law in a moral space that has been
occupied by generations before one and
so on this normalizing of these huge
transitions I think is something that
that we've always depended upon religion
to provide is sacralized yes and having
taken that away or or ignored it or try
to live without exactly without the idea
of a sacrament and we're actually at a
loss when these great transitions occur
as well because it is the case in fact
that to to engage in the integration of
sexual
with your individual life is a series of
sacrifices so for example if you get
married that's a sacrifice because it's
a sacrifice of all other people and so
it's a sacrifice of that possibility and
then to have a child is the sacrifice of
all the things that you could have done
otherwise then having that child and -
but - - as you pointed out to make that
part of a broader tradition to say that
well that is a sacrifice and there is a
loss that goes along with that but what
you gain as a consequences of if as of
immeasurable significance in contrast to
the loss and one of the things that's
really struck me in this lecture tour
that I've been doing so I've been in
about a hundred cities and one of the
things that I've been talking to people
about is its meaning and I suppose its
meaning in relationship to the
transcendent and and the necessity of
meaning as an antidote to suffering and
to malevolence and the hypothesis is
something like well meaning is to be
found in responsibility and and this is
a it's a revelation to people because
they haven't conceptualized it that way
before
it's like meaning isn't it isn't
happiness isn't self-esteem and it isn't
momentary pleasure isn't any of that
it's it's the it's the bearing of a
sacrificial burden and that that
actually works to enrich and ennoble
your life in ways that make the tragic
element of it tolerable and - and to
keep you from bitterness and so these
things that are put forward as
subjugation like the subjugation of
woman to the to the catastrophe of birth
let's say or even the the indignity of
of patriarchal Union is all of a sudden
something that you can take on as an
aspirational goal rather than something
that's a mere imposition on your on your
moment to moment freedom as a relief to
people to hear that and to know it of
course now I agree with that but there
is also the sense that in the world in
which we live
we're obviously people have been
detached to a great extent from the any
continuous religious tradition there
still is a sense of loss as a people
they don't they know that they they're
missing something but don't know quite
how to identify
and that's one reason for thinking for
them thinking that it it's been taken
away something's been stolen from them
and they look around at the people who
are at ease in the world and successful
and seem to be you know on good terms
with themselves and think of them as the
ones who've done the stealing and that
is a dangerous attitude and I think it's
well it's surely that is part of what
erupts in all these strange academic
disciplines like gender studies which
simply have as their goal the
undermining of the existing order
without anything positive to put in its
place and I don't know what that those
those academic studies recruit people
all the time
from this fund of of isolation this from
the sense a sense of loss without an
ability to identify the thing that's
been lost
that's the cult-like element of them
because they do I would say to some
degree prey on people whose
interpersonal relationships have been
irreparably damaged right I have a
hypothesis about about the feminist end
of the postmodern radical leftist
movement so and this is something I've
talked about much in public but but well
but here goes this should give me in
lots of trouble so so and there's a
variety of things that are tangled
together here so we don't know how
female biology would manifest itself
politically male biology does female
biology is going to and that's because
female political activity on the largest
possible scale is a relatively new
phenomenon so so and it isn't obviously
the case that men and women's views of
the world are going to dovetail
precisely so here's a hypothesis you
tell me what you think about this so one
thing that a woman really wants to know
about a man or perhaps you might say one
thing that feminine and he wants to know
about masculinity is that it's not a
predatory tyrant okay so and here's why
I mean first of all there's fragility
and feminine sexuality to a greater
degree than there is in male sexuality
because women bear a higher price for
sexual misadventure let's say and are
perhaps more prone to exploitation by
force but more than that part of being a
woman is having the possibility of
bringing something extraordinarily
fragile and vulnerable and valuable into
the world and the first concern might be
are you a predator fundamentally are you
a predator and so what I see happening
in the in the feminist disciplines like
gender studies is the politicization of
that accusation and the accusation is
prove to me that you're not a predator
like in your fund in the fundamental
element of your masculinity not only
historically but now because the cost of
you being a predators is too high now I
feel that that's an inappropriate I
think that's what's driving the
demolition of the idea of presumption of
innocence for example we'll start with
presumption of guilt and prove to you'll
be proved to me that you're innocent and
I think the problem with that isn't that
there are no predatory men because there
are plenty of predatory men the problem
is is that the courageous way to deal
with the problem of the predator is to
offer a hand in courageous trust and to
invite forward a partner from the
monster that's the that's the
mythological manner in which this is
supposed to be undertaken the courageous
a parker aegis part of the woman's
journey let's say is to face the
monstrosity of a man and to invite out
of that something more noble to emerge
and there's courage in that in genuine
risk and I think that that's foregone in
the accusation process and then the the
other element of that seems to me to be
that well if you are a predator and
you're irredeemable in your predatory
nature then the best thing to do is to
render you harmless and if we're going
to obscure the relationship between
competence and power and assume that all
of your striving upward is merely a
manifestation of power then what we'll
do is we can you as much as possible so
that harmlessness can replace virtue and
I see all of that driving these
resentful disciplines in there and the
reason am is the amass key
with the man yeah that's the evil queen
yeah yeah because we have the evil king
right that's the tyrannical patriarchy
well the evil queen is lurking somewhere
yes so the problem is I know it a lot of
this is true but our society does not
seem to have the capacity to put that to
one side and celebrates the normal the
the the fact that most men and most
women are not like that and that there
is there is a natural desire and need of
the sexes to love each other to be
united and to create children and so on
and that that the old stability that
that was built upon this has gone so I
mean that and nobody wants nobody in the
intellectual world wants to celebrate
there so so I just I had this interview
a few a month ago or so with a woman
from GQ and she was fully on board the
the predatory mail train let's say and
you know when people like that interview
me they start talking about the
patriarchy and I say well I I don't
believe in the patriarchy I don't buy
that conceptual structure what's so
interesting and this has happened more
and more over the years as they've
developed us first of all the person
that I would be talking to had some idea
that it was hypothetically possible to
reject the idea of the patriarchy but
now when I say I don't believe in it
it's it's that ideas meant with stunned
disbelief it's like what what do you
mean
you don't believe in the tyrannical
Patriot everyone knows that's true and I
think well so here's your hypothesis so
this is the hypothesis that throw
history the fundamental relationship
between man and woman is one of
parasitism and exploitation that's it
and so and that's the case I guess until
1960 and the publication of The Feminine
Mystique or something like that but
that's the entire course of human
history and then when the when it seems
to me that the appropriate story is that
men and women labored mightily under
their terrible constraints for for
uncounted centuries cooperating together
by and large to to build some body
of security and and freedom and
stability so that they could raise
children and have a somewhat harmonious
and productive life and all of a sudden
it's become not only questionable to put
forth that as a proposition but somehow
tyrannical in it in in essence just for
positing it as a reality but that's
partly because isn't it because of this
peculiar view that the underlying all
this there's a kind of social structure
that would this is being created the
distinction between men and women
doesn't have its basis in nature it's
its basis is in the institutions that we
have created and since we created them
we can change them that there is there's
been it's sort of a kind of almost
hysterical invasion of everything by the
idea of human choice if there is if
there is a structure to the relation
between men and women then we ought to
be able to change it and of course chain
we might mean that I have to change my
sex in order to to conform to the way
things are but that also has become a
choice well and is is is not a very very
constant focus on division whether
between man and woman or between left
and right orbit or between this race in
that race or any other way in which we
might we might divide people according
to groups isn't that very polarized
fracture that fractured polarization a
sign of a loss of a common human culture
of a universal plane in which we all we
all are as human beings and and so if if
that that's if that's if that is so I
suppose what I state to be so very
urgent in our time and and I wonder it
might be difficult to find anyone who at
least when you go down to a high enough
level of resolution as you say Jordan
would not think this is true that we
must recover that sense of ourselves as
entities that participate in a universal
and transcendent plane that we have a
common cult
that I see myself in the other as you
were saying earlier Roger and I'd like
to have both of your thoughts on what
strategies were means for that recovery
and perhaps we can focus particularly on
the the the the questions that we
started with with art music you've
written too extensively an architecture
of course Roger and you've thought long
and hard about the humanities Jordan
what is it what is the character of
recovery how do we bring that about well
if I may begin I think that there are
well first of all you have to identify
those aspects of the human condition
that move of their own accord towards
reconciliation you know a rather than
conflict and and division of the sort
that you're referring to and we are very
familiar with them it's not just that
just love which of course is something
very complex in and can't be can't be
just conjured from the skies but there
are there are other aspects of our
condition that we can educate through
first first of all through studying
examples and then through imitation and
then through self-discipline obviously
forgiveness is one of these things and
the habit of putting yourself in another
person's perspective looking at yourself
from outside and wondering whether you
know the you are as so seen acceptable
to yourself all those you know of course
again religion of the Christian religion
at least was built upon that's kind of
intellectual discipline the discipline
of seeing your neighbor as yourself and
seeing yourself therefore as a mere
neighbor and I I suspect that you have
we have to revive those basic moral
disciplines not for the use of people
who don't have the overarching faith
their belief in transcendental judgment
into which we will be all calls but whom
nevertheless have to be shown that we do
live our lives as an object of judgment
nevertheless and here are some guides
you know just read Anna Karenina for
example I know it takes a long time for
facebook addicted youth to read Anna
Karenina but they still hope you know
and and they're likely to listen to it
so so well because maybe more people can
listen then can read I mean so so let's
let's think about literature for a bit
and so now if you read something like a
Dostoyevsky novel or Anna Karenina
you're not really reading the account of
a single person's life what you're
reading is it's like the author has
taken a variety of lives and amalgamated
them and unified them into something
that's like a it's like a compilation of
lives so it's life it's like life writ
large so that's what fiction is it's
more true than than reality because just
like a mathematical abstraction can be
more real than the thing that it
represents in some sense the fiction is
it's like it's like a portrait if you
sit for a portrait you'll sit and the
artist will paint you and then you'll
sit again and then you'll sit again and
then you'll sit again and so the
portrait is actually a composite of you
and so it's got a richness sometimes
that a photograph can't match and a
fictional character is actually a
composite of many people and so the
opportunity to read a great work of
fiction is the opportunity to place
yourself in the perspective not of
merely another person like you do in
normal discourse in the mundane setting
but to place yourself in the perspective
of a compiled character so you
experienced that extraordinarily
powerfully with Dostoyevsky's crime and
punishment to put myself in the position
of this student who was nihilistic and
who had every reason to commit murder
and it's an unbelievably intense novel
because everybody in the novel is hyper
real and
we think of fiction as falsity or or or
or as untruth and it's not it's it's
it's abstraction an abstraction isn't
untruth it's it's more than truth often
and so the humanities can help us walk
through the souls of others and because
we can imitate and it's one of our
primary remarkable miraculous abilities
we can imitate the the compiled
characters that we encounter in
literature and mythology and religion
and that does help flesh us out and
ennoble us and we can we can I just
wrote the foreword to Solzhenitsyn's
fiftieth anniversary version of The
Gulag Archipelago the abridged version
and I ran across his fervent wish that
people could learn from what he
communicated all the horror and
suffering to put themselves in the
position of both the perpetrator and the
and the accused simultaneously and to
decide that that's not the road to walk
down and so the advantage of placing
yourself in the position of other people
is that if they're good people then you
can be like them and if they're not good
people then you can avoid that pathway
and then you don't have to learn that
through through the agony of direct
personal experience in the short span of
your life there's nothing more there's
nothing greater than you can do for
people than to introduce them into those
patterns stories so that they can gain
from the catastrophes of the past mmm no
I agree with that oh but of course in
fiction one's also concerned to identify
if you're writing fiction identify with
a character in order to understand that
character because it's not as though you
can you can't actually grasp a character
from the outside you have to be able to
see through his eyes what it what the
world is in which he is and that is I
think an exercise of the imagination
which I value greatly and you don't
necessarily come to the conclusion that
therefore I don't want to be like that
it might be just enough to say now I see
that that's a possible human being and
your knowledge of the possibilities is
amplified and your sense your ability to
position yourself in those possibilities
also I think right so that's a matter of
differentiation as well as direction yes
no no I think sometimes in my more dire
moments that this opposition to cultural
appropriation right so the idea that I'm
not allowed anymore to imagine myself
safe fictionally as a woman or us or as
a character from another ethnicity or
even to play the role that role as an
actor I think that it's it's part of the
assault on the idea of the individual
and the nonzero-sum game because it
precludes the possibility that I can
take on the role of another in an
understanding manner and actually
facilitate a dialogue and that
undermines the claim I would say that
everything is only a secondary
consequence of power because if I can
actually bridge that gap well then I'm
not isolated in my group or my ethnicity
or whatever it is I can I can become
partly you and we can communicate and I
would say because of that literature and
art is a great threat to ideology
especially of the group identity kind
and of course they're perfectly aware of
that which is why the radicals on that
side of the equation are doing
everything they can to to reporter from
the New York Times who wrote a rather
scurrilous piece about me she had done
the literature degree at at Columbia a
bright woman and she told me in all
honesty and apparent transparency that
she had no idea this is how deep this is
this has become saturated into our
culture she had no idea until she until
she had graduated from Columbia that
there was any other way of reading a
work of literature except through the
postmodern lens and the postmodern lens
is well who are the groups that are
being represented and what power games
are at play and who benefits and and I
mean I don't know if because she turned
out to be quite a strange person but so
I have no idea if that if that was a
ploy on her part or whether that was
like a like a naive what would you call
confession but it's increasingly the
case that that is how literature is
taught in my home province of Ontario
the Elementary Teachers Federation of
Ontario wants to start teaching
literature from a postmodern critical
perspective in elementary school to
demolish it well there we are I mean I'm
in favor of cultural cultural
appropriation I mean I'm a product of it
i appropriately idea of the English
gentleman and you know and I try and
made myself be it and I know it's a
failure because that's part of doing it
well yeah yeah i but i've understood the
world from the inside in another way but
in I just wrote a book of stories which
was just reviewed by somebody who says
you know this these stories make
cultural appropriation into a virtue and
so I felt good about that they they
begin with a an inside view of the
psyche of a terrorist of an Arab
terrorists who's who has a legacy of
vengeance and who is a failure and whose
loss I try to make real in in the
feelings of the reader as he reads it
and and then the subsequent stories show
the same kind of loss in completely
different people I wanted to bring up
that book of stories actually souls in
Twilight by Sir Roger Scruton it's a
series of five short stories of five I
think is that five short stories each
which are portraits of a character at a
certain moment in time I think it's safe
to say Roger that they're all tragic
stories in a sense
what I found so moving about those
stories is that these are individuals in
states of dislocation anchor 'less
seeking depth meaning truth stability
and yet in their confusion in their
darkness willing against that very thing
that they seek or you might say
violating or transgressing that sacred
thing that they're longing for that's
not what's beautiful about
book what's beautiful is that in the
reading the reader her or himself comes
to a sense of what that longing is for
positively a sense of the the stability
of love or of home or of relationship
and and and I suppose what I want to ask
following up on this is that that seems
to me a profoundly redemptive vision
that you have in that in those beautiful
stories Roger and that that it's showing
the persistence of the beautiful and of
the good even in its absence that I can
read that story and have a perception of
what positively I am I am looking for
and just to refer to it something that
you say in in one of your books toward
and that that even through an experience
of evil one can develop an apprehension
of what the good is and wondering if you
could each say something about the that
you know either
either there is a reality to these
transcendent things where there is not
if it either just a construct goodness
or beauty and truth or they have a
transcendent and and sovereign
persistent reality and I'm wondering if
you can each say something about the the
persistence or sovereignty of these
things even amidst our darkness and
suffering well I I would say that in
tragedy when tragedy is really effective
there is a Redemption offered in this
through suffering that the the the the
we we encounter the possibility in
tragedy that a human being can through
the most noble motives also bring about
on a pot down upon himself destruction
and destruction is no different from the
destruction it's going to afflict all of
us in the end anyway but here is
somebody who who has faced it down in
some way that his nobility his nobility
of nature
and his ability to go out towards others
in a condition of love and Rickon
reconciliation has not been taken away
from him and the spectacle of that is
all the more intense because
nevertheless the you know death
intervenes and takes him away as it will
take you and me away but without having
had the chance to reveal a nobility or
even to acquire it you know I think that
for that reason it's very important that
in literature the noble characters are
seen in a condition of loss sometimes
that their and their their Redemption
comes because even though they've lost
what we all must in the end lose there
is that in them which is struggling
towards reconciliation with their own
condition and with others it's the sense
that they are living as another and not
as herself
you know that's tears I think it's a
crucial thing that the Gulag Archipelago
is often viewed as an endless
documentation of the horrors of the
Soviet enterprise but it was an
investigation it was an experiment in
literary investigation and that isn't
what the book is about the book is about
Solzhenitsyn's observations of people in
those terrible situations who did not
contribute to the terror and who
transcended it and the unbelievably
power powerful impact observing that had
on him and the personal transformation
he underwent as a consequence of
observing those people and the decision
he made because of seeing them in their
ultimately tragic circumstances
transcend that to to to transform his
life from the bottom up and to write
this great book and to reveal the utter
catastrophe of that entire ideological
movement and so you do see the light
most clearly when it's superimposed
against the darkest possible background
and so and great literature which pulls
people way down into the depths and in
in this in this in this compiled
fictional manner
then it also does at the same time
highlight what's what's what's the
opposite of that so I tell it by reading
of your your your your work both of you
there's an implicitly theological
character here and we can't speak about
the transcendent in a certain sense
without being theological and you know
why is it that we can't just the lights
just can't be completely shut out I mean
if if if evil and darkness were the
sovereign principles as we say
metaphysically well they could it could
just be all the lights could just be
completely blackened and yet that's not
what we see and I'm wondering if you
would each comment on the what you take
to be the I think what wouldn't what
might be a theological articulation of
the facts on the ground if the facts are
that you can't shut the lights right out
that they're still there what what's
going on there I totally agree with what
Jordan said about the Gulag Archipelago
and that goes back to just ask is from
the House of the Dead
you know his account of being in a
Tsarist much milder with kind of
imprisonment but nevertheless it was
full of almost a vacation compared to
comparison I agree but nevertheless he
described these characters who for whom
that everything had been taken away but
he also notes that in each of them you I
can find the spark of God something
which Janacek repeated when he made this
into the into that wonderful libretto
for his opera and anyon I try to show in
music how these derelict characters will
suddenly shine with that with that light
from another source but it doesn't come
just from what they are in that those
circumstances but from something higher
and I think you know I would say one is
always obliged to use metaphors when we
get to this point but it is true that
to that you can find in someone even in
the most deprived and desolate
circumstances that on which you can blow
to cause the spark once again to delight
up inside him and that is as far as we
get to meeting God but there is no
reason to think that we need to get any
further in my view that's what people
everybody saw in Maximilian Kolbe when
he offered himself in the in Auschwitz
for you know to as a sacrifice and while
he was canonized you know suddenly you
see that there is something else in all
of us in which in in circumstances
however severe and deprived will will
shine from it with a different light and
make those circumstances worthwhile
because they produced that light it
could be in some sense the mercy of God
that keeps him hidden from us because if
you imagine that your sacred duty is to
blow on those embers that you described
even among people who are in desolate
straits then every time you fail to take
that opportunity then you tilt things
badly towards what they shouldn't be
tilted towards and it could be that the
revelation of your inadequacy in the
face of that moral duty which would be
in some sense equivalent to an encounter
with God would be enough to tear you
into pieces
and so maybe you get glimpses of that
now and then because that's that's all
you and your current depraved moral
state could stand of seeing of the face
of God I think there's something to that
that's what Seimone very says things to
that effect I think yeah and yes I often
heard in the old communist days when I
used to travel around Eastern Europe and
and meet people who are in really dire
straits they said similar things you
know that that
that God would reveal himself but in
these circumstances the revelation will
be something too strong what I could
bear that's a beautiful image you've
given us Roger of blowing on the embers
within blowing on the embers of
transcendence I'd ask you both about the
forms of culture and institutional life
that produce that blowing on the embers
in the individual it seems to me both of
you have a very deep sense of the
dignity of the human individual of the
individuals connection to the
transcendent the grounding fact of our
existence what would be the forms of
culture that we would say to be
necessary or most most inclined to
foster in the individual that blowing of
the flame well I think the most
accessible form for most people is music
and music to me is the most
representational form of art because I
think that the world is made out of
patterns and we perceive some patterns
as objects but fundamentally its
patterns and what you want is all the
patterns of the world to interact
harmoniously and in something where
every element is related intelligibly to
every other element and I think that
when your life is in harmony that you
can feel that and when you're dancing to
beautiful music you're acting that out
it's the music is the is the music of
the spheres and you're participating in
the patterning of your being in
accordance with that structure and that
gives you an intimation of of
transcendence and and it's it's not
criticized about that's the thing that's
so lovely about it is even as our
society has become more cynical and more
self-destructive and more
deconstructionist the power of music has
in fact grown because it speaks to that
eternal harmony and the reality of that
eternal harmony in a way that that mere
intellect cannot deny and I mean I was
always amused I went to this show The
Ramones a punk band from New York it was
the loudest car
I never heard bye-bye a good factor of
10 my ears rang for like 3 days
afterwards and there were all these like
nihilistic punk rockers all crammed into
this theater and below me
there was a mosh pit and it was like
ants on a frying pan they were just
smashing into each other and throwing
people around up above them and it was
quite rough and they're all having this
beautifully transcendent musical
experience which belied all of their
nihilism and it was and they absolutely
thrived on it it was like an even the
lyrics were harsh and nihilistic but it
didn't matter because the music even if
it's right even if had in its rough form
was something that United them in the
sense of this like pattern beauty and
brought them together and so exposure to
music that's people died without music
it's like music is everything I mean
it's not everything but I beg it's every
degree about about the beauty of this
particular experience I think actually
dancing is an extremely important
phenomenon partly because traditionally
dancing was dancing with someone the
width has been taken out of dancing and
the head bashing and so on that goes on
with heavy metal and the Reich is
dancing against someone you know that
the witness of the dance is that there's
something real we see it in Scottish
reels and things like that where the
whole community is dancing in an orderly
way recognizing that their need for law
and order and taking pleasure in it now
I find that a very near to a
transcendent experience I feel a kind of
narcissism has crept into them the dance
through recent forms of dance music but
I mean that's my old geezer attitude or
or is or is or is it simply to say that
there that that the principle itself is
sovereign everyone thinks about the
logic for example of Dante's Inferno
which because evermore degraded forms of
knowing and loving
that that the mechanism of the the
nature you might say the nature of the
soul is the same at the top of paradise
as it is at the at the bottom of Inferno
but it has these infinite gradations of
wholeness and so I don't think we have
to say that that that the the mosh pit
is is is is is equivalent as a work of
art to to Beethoven or Palestrina or
Yana check but rather that perhaps
what's going on in in in that is
nonetheless a longing for the pattern
and the the recognition of the other
that you use you say but but yes but
your original question was how do we how
do we coax people back into that into a
life which is based on the recognition
of the other rather than the
gratification of the self because that's
essentially what we're talking about I
think within today at least
and I would say teaching people how to
help others the role of the teacher it's
a very dignified one but it it is only
so if the teacher actually thinks that
he is helping the pupil to a body of
knowledge that he has access to and that
sense of helping other people is a very
rare thing and it's it's made more rare
by the the welfare state and the ready
availability of subsidies for subsidized
life without leaning on any particular
person you know and I think relations of
dependence are actually very positive if
they are accepted on both sides you know
and I think it's something that we don't
teach and the boy scouts movement and
all that they used to teach young people
these things teach people how to go out
and help those who needed them and how
to make those little Saturday to day
sacrifices and eventually through the
process of imitation and imagination
a character grows based on that I feel
that there isn't any obstacle to this
it's a very simple form of Education all
of us can do it and all of us who have
children do do it I'm sure Jordan does
it with his children the same as I with
mine of course it you know you're always
disappointed they always go away into
their court corner with their with their
wretched little iPhones and so on but
nevertheless it some of it rubs off and
you know that in the long run they will
be capable not just of finding love but
also of offering forgiveness and and
working for reconciliation I don't think
in the sort of narcissistic culture
which is propagated by the media and by
the universities that that they're being
pointed in that direction that is true
but then it's up to us to point them in
another direction I think as an academic
we talked already about that place where
the meaning and the fact are conjoined
and that's the proper place to lecture
from because people who lecture
constantly make the presumption that
they're there to deliver a set of facts
but there's an infinite set of facts and
so at the very least you have to select
the facts and there's a mechanism that
selects the facts what what you want to
do as an academic is is tell your
students through through direct
discourse and also through action about
something that you've encountered that's
that you've fallen in love with and to
and to communicate the love that you
have for that the love for literature
and and not to say well you should read
this book but to say well here's this
book and here's what it can open up for
you and this is how it does it and and
this is what you'll gain from it it's an
inestimable gain and there's some
struggle in it but but there's a there's
something in it that's of unbelievable
utility and you have to believe that in
order to communicate it and then that's
hope that opens one of those doors you
know and maybe some students will step
through that and think well maybe that
sounds like something I need I'm in this
dire situation and I need something I
need a life raft
need a they need something to boy me
upward and it's going to take some
effort obviously because nothing
worthwhile comes without effort to
communicate that commitment you have to
these to these to these phenomena that
phenomena that we already talked about
to beauty and to truth and to literature
and enter the classics in the humanities
it isn't enough just to say what they
are and to transmit them it's to it's to
manifest yourself as a living part of
that tradition and to and to show
yourself thereby as a model for living
out as much as you can what that
tradition represents and to show that
that's so much better than like a
short-term pleasure seeking nihilism
that they're not even in the same
conceptual universe and people are far
more open to that they know already
people know especially when they're hurt
they know that happiness is fleeting and
that suffering requires a sustaining
meaning everyone who's lived knows that
and so to say well here's some balm for
the suffering and it's profound and deep
and and here's what it's meant to me and
here's how you can incorporate it into
your life it's like people are
absolutely starving for that or dying of
thirst for that I mean this connects
with what you earlier said about the
curriculum that the old way of teaching
the humanities was in that manner as
objects of love this is what I have
loved what previous generations have
loved to and handed on to me here try it
out and you will love it too whereas the
postmodern a curriculum is a curriculum
of hatred it's directed against our
cultural inheritance one after another
the works are paraded before us stripped
naked and thrashed you know by what by
revealing whatever ideology or power
structure is being concealed within them
and that of course is not why they were
written and it's not how they should be
understood it's not why they survived an
example like this is the best that the
best of us could produce and it's
nothing why should you bother doing it
and it means that students who go
through that curriculum come out with a
sense of the hopelessness of everything
and thus are successfully educated by
postmodernist standards yeah yeah I
suppose that's right but you know
there's no reason why one should one
should accept this one all all good
things begin in the in small areas
because because two or three people you
know well as Christ said two or three
are gathered in my name you know there
am i with you but the same is is in all
cultural activities it's a perhaps a
friendship will will be game it will
start up a reading group and out of that
reading group there'll be others come in
gradually if it's founded on love of the
thing that's being studied and offered
it will always triumph in the long run
over this negativity the problem is the
negativity is subsidized is subsidized
by universities who are paid for by
governments who are paid for by
taxpayers and so on and the the answer
is to take away those subsidies and and
deprive education completely of money
and it will be back with us again that's
right I super I suggested something like
that in public in Canada not so long ago
to cut the budgets of the universities
across the board by 25 percent and let
them sort themselves out because but the
the no subsidy idea at least forces
those who provide education to do it
purely on its merits and the fact that
these counterproductive disciplines
let's say have been subsidized for so
long has given them a power that's far
far outstrips their their credibility
and their attractiveness alright now I
wanted to to point out will this this
this chat may be seen by a few people
online at some point and draw attention
to vet that we're all wearing the
poppies of course is a is is is is this
symbol of respect and memory for an
inheritance of our own past
for the the suffering that has given us
or at least protected and given us so
much that we hold dear
I'd like to ask you both about memory
and the inheritance of the past and and
what it means to have a pedagogy what it
means to have a pedagogy of the
transcendent in relation to our past how
do you open open those those those
doorways and and perhaps a if if the
spirit moves you to speak about works
that you love that you've been able to
open up to others one of the reasons for
remembering you know in the way that we
remember the Armistice in the First
World War one of the reasons is is
gratitude and gratitude is in short
supply in our societies today and it's
the it's the the greatest gift that we
can offer in fact as sorts of people who
are dead because what else can we do
except to acknowledge what their
sacrifice so I think that gratitude is a
fundamental part of memory there are of
course accumulations of guilts and and
so on
and those are being emphasized all the
time in the postmodern curriculum all
the all the ways in which we are not
entitled to our inheritance but I would
think in the face of that we have to
insist on the ways that we are entitled
to that inheritance if people have died
for it forth and for our sake you know
that is a fantastic in title that we
enjoy and we should feel grateful to
them for that I mean when it comes to no
actual works or of art or whatever which
have opened the sense of the depth of
one's own inheritance that I think is a
very interesting question as so many of
them but but just to mention only one
the bar b-minor mass to me that's a door
into the end
they hit the hold the whole European
inheritance going back to the
crucifixion clarity there it all is
encapsulated in music music you know
celebrating the universal claims of the
Roman Catholic Church were written by a
Protestant you know that it's and
offered as a gift you know to mankind
and there it is and there's such things
so transcend any any minor historical
details that one recognizes that that is
what the past really is for one that
great depth of inheritance that can't be
enumerated but just enjoy it just to
follow up before we turn to Jordan Roger
at the beginning you talked about a how
great literature great writing is
writing in which the reader finds
himself finds herself taking Bach's mass
and B minor you've spoken about the this
unfolding of the self that is found in
these great works or the reflection of
the self I know at least I think you've
written about the the unfolding of the
theme in in in in of that mass in
particular but and certainly in other
other of your writings the unfolding of
the theme and music could you say
something about the I know there's a
huge question but the way in which the
unfolding of the theme in music is an
unfolding of the self it's a really
provocative way of putting it it is true
that when you listen to a theme in music
you are not listening to a sequence of
notes something begins in that first
note and endures to the final note and
it goes on all the way through even
though there are spells of silence it's
still going on in the silence so that
our ability to hear something as a theme
is already a contribution that we make
it comes out of us so we've identified
with that mu
movement that movement is it's there in
the world because it's there in us but
but in so many ways
all our inner life is interrupted and
unfulfilled and it's full of things that
start up and then beat round and I think
that is one of the fundamental
experiences of human beings that there's
an inner disorder that things never
actually come to a conclusion but here
uniquely movements begin and come to a
conclusion this is and that conclusion
is is complete
it's a satisfaction of the unsaturated
nature of the first movement of the
first beginning theme and it's an an
experience what why do we value that I
think we value a value it in the same
way as we value tragedy because it gives
completion and closure to things that
otherwise wouldn't ever have them and
things that are transient as well
because it does have a beginning and an
end and the end doesn't invalidate the
utility of the of the entity that's
right hmm so in the gratitude I mean
that was that was exactly the theme that
sprung to mind for me
as soon as you asked that question I
mean one of the things that I found find
profoundly disquieting about the modern
radical what would you call it ideology
that is so no so unfortunately dominant
on campuses among young people is that
it's unbelievably ungrateful and when I
when I walk outside and there's not a
riot and death in the streets I'm having
a good day
that's my sense of history it's like I'm
constantly staggered by the fact that so
much works all the time it's absolutely
I met this guy a while back and he'd
been in a motorcycle accident
he really got hurt man he was he was
pretty much half destroyed and he worked
as a telephone lineman he worked with
this guy who had Parkinson's disease who
had was equally destroyed in a slightly
different way and the two of them
together could climb up a telephone pole
and continue their job and I thought
this unbelievable infrastructure we have
that
just an absolute bloody unknowing
ongoing miracle is sustained by people
exactly like that you know they're
having very difficult lives in a country
like Canada they go out in the middle of
the bloody winter where you die it's
frigid and something breaks and they fix
it and the lights are on the lights are
on all the time and I come to somewhere
like Europe and to me it's an absolutely
overwhelming experience to see Kings
Chapel today to wander around this city
I just staggered that people produce
this and so amazed that we could do it
and so grateful that it exists it we
were talking about King's chapel the
people who started it didn't live to see
its completion they were they were
driven by this nobility of transcendent
vision and they produced these enduring
forms and out of the bloody misery of
history we've erected all this
spectacular infrastructure that we're so
fortunate to be part of them the none of
that gratitude is taught and it's partly
not taught because people have no sense
of the absolute catastrophe of history I
mean for me the Hobbs it's like nasty
brutish and short that the simplest and
most likely social circumstances
catastrophe punctuated by hell and to
see that not happening in a sustained
manner constantly and to see things
improving around us and and to be
reliable in that manner and then not to
be grateful for that it's like it's an
unbelievable combination of ignorance
and wilf ignorance ingratitude and
willful blindness and it does no-one
soul any good it's so good to walk down
the streets of a beautiful town like
this and to be open mouthed in
non-ironic amazement at what's here and
so and to not instill that sense and
young people to for them to understand
that they are standing on the bones of
generations of people who suffered to
make this possible despite all their
errors and have brought this forward
it's like yeah well Hobbs is a very
salutary lesson actually because he did
look into the abyss
and stepped back from it and reported on
it and and we and as did Solzhenitsyn
and we post-war baby boomers haven't had
that experience and I had a little
glimpse of it in the old communist days
but we only saw the edge of it then you
know but still the scent the sense that
it is there always beneath your feet and
that the crust is as thin as it it can
be in certain places that I think is
something that young people do need to
be taught without making them get gloomy
about it but to recognize that they
they're lucky a last question before we
open up for a few questions here it
seems to me that the the
backward-looking that we've talked about
you had a wonderful phrase a wide-eyed
open-mouthed non-ironic engagement I
think he said walking around this
transcendently beautiful town of
Cambridge which houses this August and
ancient and beautiful institution we you
mentioned Jordan was seeing the King's
chapel earlier today that those who
started the work knew they wouldn't be
those who would finish and those who
finished knew they had inherited to work
that they had not themselves begun and
so I suppose I want to ask we've talked
about the the the the necessity to turn
back with gratitude to the Past to our
inherited past and I want to talk also
about the possibility of building in a
creation these chapels and buildings
were built at some time you yourself are
a composer both of you authors of books
that many many people have found depth
and truth in so I want to to ask about
the possibilities for for for
Renaissance for rebuilding or building a
new at new buildings new forms of
community new forms of art perhaps new
buildings of old forms of architecture
new colleges and universities new
more healthy and beautiful forms of
courtship new forms of flourishing arts
and music it seems to me so important
that that we not lose sight of the fact
that precisely the abiding truth of the
transcendent in us gives us hope to to
answer that call yeah it must be the
case that when when describing our
cultural inheritance we are not just
describing something that's gone we must
be describing something of which we are
still apart and which we which has to
changed as we are changing to
accommodate us all this was said by
Eliot in tradition and the individual
talent you know that that the artist
must be constantly trying to say that
new thing that that he came into the
world to say but he can only say it if
he adapts his style to the the
inheritance of the tradition thereby
transforming the tradition and
transforming himself and we all there
and there is no formula for doing this
because a formula is precisely what what
destroys the creative act but we have to
assume that new things will come and
they will come through as as they always
did in the past through fasting and
prayer you know and the occasional glass
of wine in my case Jordan well we could
concentrate I suppose on building the
future instead of criticizing the past
I mean it's necessary to decompose to
reconstruct you know those those acts
can't be separated but the decomposition
is the prerequisite for the
reconstruction and you know what I've
been recommending to people is that they
they start on whatever scale they can
start on with whatever's in front of
them because they have more in front of
them than they think these these these
these circumscribed areas that these
small places that people can call their
own even if it's the only their room
you can start to do something creative
and beautiful there I mean I've
suggested to people that they start by
putting the room in order and that
implies a purpose it's like well your
room is somewhere that you exist it's
it's it's a place that surrounds you
that tells you how to be is put it in
order so at least it isn't
screaming chaos at you in a
soul-destroying manner make it pristine
and and and and orderly in in a fashion
that suits what you're aiming at so have
a name and then this is perhaps a
chapter in my next book well maybe you
start by putting your room in order and
then you make it beautiful and then you
learn how to make something beautiful
and to make something beautiful is to
make it worthwhile and to participate in
that transcendent meet and in that
transcendence maybe you need one
certainly and for your future self which
is also others you know this idea that
people are fed even of self
gratification let's say as an antidote
to nihilism well take your pleasure in
the moment it doesn't even work for you
because you're stuck with you tomorrow
and you next week and so even to treat
yourself properly is to treat yourself
as part of an ongoing community but I
would say start by you start in the
world if you have some wisdom and some
humility by taking the potential that
lies dormant in front of you and
interacting with it in the logos like
manner with truth and with love and by
transforming that potential into
whatever you can create out of it that's
good and even if it's it won't be small
if you do that you can transform your
whole household by transforming your
room you can transform your whole
neighborhood by transforming your house
like these things spread very very
rapidly and that is right there in front
of you you know and people think they're
impoverished now that they don't have
any opportunity and that and the
opportunity is hidden from them by their
by their by their unwillingness to take
the steps that are necessary to put what
they could put in front of them in order
and and and to and to produce the beauty
instead of the ugliness where they could
do that and I don't think there is
anything more powerful than that that
works I've had thousands of people
tell me that it works you know
personally and come and talk to me every
day now on the street and say my life
was in terrible disorder I had no vision
I wasn't abiding by the truth my
relationships were fragmented I've
decided to make something of myself
whatever that might be
I've decided to adopt more
responsibility and to tell the truth and
things are incomparably better and so
that's that's there for everyone to take
and regardless of your circumstances and
I know that some people have what appear
to be larger opportunities and more
privileged in front of them but that
also makes they're commensurate and
moral responsibility larger so there's a
certain balancing that's a natural
consequence of that so now recognizing
the nature of the finite there's a train
one of us needs to catch we're going to
have to draw this conversation to a
close but not before we've all had a
chance to thank both of you for
everything you do to fan the flames of
the transcendent for your readers for
your listeners for all of us thank you
very much both of you
[Applause]